# Ryan Marcus

Los Alamos, NM 505-500-4365 ryan@rmarcus.info

# **PROFILE**

I am a Ph.D. student in computer science at Brandeis University. My research currently focuses on cloud databases and scheduling problems. I graduated with honors from the University of Arizona, where I took courses in computer science, gender and women's studies, and mathematics.

# **EDUCATION**

Brandeis University, 2014 - now. Ph.D. student in Computer Science.

- Big Data Analysis
- Abstract Algebra
- Statistical Machine Learning
- Database Systems

- Operating Systems
- Theory of Computation
- Artificial Intelligence
- Distributed Systems

University of Arizona Honors College, 2010-2014. Computer science, mathematics and gender studies.

- Compilers
- Databases
- Parallel Programming
- Object Oriented Programming

- Algorithms
- Symbolic Logic
- Analytic Geometry
- Discrete Math

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## Brandeis University with Dr. Olga Papaemmanouil 2014 - now

Researching cloud database systems, focus on applying machine learning algorithms to query scheduling as well as other classically hard problems.

# Los Alamos National Laboratory (HPC-5) with Cornell Wright 2014 - 2015

Developed a framework for automatic performance analysis using machine learning to extract insights from hotspot profiles, MPI traces, and version control systems. Achieved a drastic reduction in memory usage in a large hydrodynamics code.

# The University of Arizona with Dr. Richard Snodgrass 2013-2014

Worked on the AMELIE project, a toolkit to automatically generate casual models of database performance. I created the initial prototype and test suite.

## Los Alamos National Laboratory (AET-6) with Dr. William Ward 2013

Worked on laboratory's 3D reconstruction code, RECON. Designed parallel versions of serial algorithms and implemented them on GPGPUs. Designed a novel, fast algorithm to approximate median filters. Improved the performance of RECON by a factor of three.

# The University of Arizona with Dr. Shaughan Lavine 2012-2013

Developed novel Monte Carlo algorithm functional dependency discovery in large databases. We were able to optimize several production database schemas at the UofA.

# Los Alamos National Laboratory (XCP-3) with Dr. Larry Cox 2009-2012

Worked on Los Alamos' premier Monte Carlo particle transport code, MCNP. Design exascale applications as well as working with a large Fortran project. Presented at SC10 and SC11.

# Arizona College Debate Team 2010-2014

Competitive collegiate policy debate. Synthesized thousands of scholarly articles into succinct arguments. Advanced to the top 10%, participating at three national championships. Volunteer debate coach for Catalina Foothills High School.

## **PAPERS**

Marcus, Ryan; Susaya, Vladimir; Yatskar, Anna. "Nothing Left to Learn: A Technique for Detecting Convergence in Big Data Exploration"; 2015

Marcus, Ryan C. "<u>Techniques for Automated Performance Analysis</u>" LA-UR-14-26577, OSTI 1154980; 2014

Marcus, Ryan C; Ward, William C. "DP: a Fast Median Filter Approximation" LA-UR-13-25331, OSTI 1088342; 2013

Marcus, Ryan C. "MCMini: Monte Carlo on GPGPU" LA-UR-12-23206, OSTI 1047072; 2012

Cox, Lawrence J; Marcus, Ryan C. "Developing a Monte Carlo mini-app for exascale co-design" LA-UR-11-06085, OSTI 1074563; 2011

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

Godby, Brionne ; Leeman-Munk, Rachel ; Marcus, Ryan. "Execution Plan Compiler for Arbitrary Join Orderings" ; 2014

Marcus, Ryan C. "<u>Machine Learning for Humans</u>" for the Los Alamos National Laboratory Data Science Summer School; 2015.

Marcus, Ryan C. "Shared Memory for Many-Core: A Hydrodynamics Case Study" for the Los Alamos National Laboratory Research Symposium, LA-UR-15-25303; 2015.

## **POSTERS**

Marcus, Ryan C. "<u>Matriarch: A Framework for Automated Performance Analysis</u>" for the Los Alamos National Laboratory Research Symposium; 2014.

#### **AWARDS**

- Codestellation Hackathon <u>Judge's Pick</u> for <u>Pandat</u> (Fall 15)
- Computer Science <u>Outstanding Teaching Fellow Award</u> (Fall 14/Spring 15)
- 3-Day Startup Challenge Winner (2015)
- Brandeis University Michtom Fellowship (2014)
- National Debate Scholar, Summa Cum Laude (2013)